of you who have not joined our seminars before
um we have presentations that are uh 20 to 35
minutes in length with a bit of flexibility there
and we kindly ask that you keep your microphones
muted during the presentation so as not to
disturb the presenter and if you're struggling
with a connection please turn your video off
because that can help to improve the connection
after the seminar we'll have chance for a 10
10-15 minute question and discussion session
if you don't want to ask your question uh
online um please type it into the chat and
i can read it out to the to the presenter and as
always we've got life going on around us um so if
you have to go please uh get up and go it's not a
problem at all um and at the end of the seminars
we have a chance uh for a bit of a catch-up if
anybody's interested a bit of a social aspect to
the seminars uh and this is is is not recorded so
it's it's a relaxed environment and so today i'm
really pleased that we've got uh gemma richardson
from uh the bgs here in the uk and she's going to
be talking to us today about uh space weather so
i will hand over to you gemma okay thanks greg
okay so hi everyone as as greg said i'm here from
the british geological survey um i've not put
everybody's name on the talk because there's lots
of people in the j magnussen team who i'm sure
i'm stealing some of their work but i will
give them full credit in due course i'm sure
um so yeah today i'm going to talk about space
weather and its impact on grounded technology
um so i thought i'd start by doing a quick kind of
introduction to space weather i'm aware that for
a lot of you space weather impacts on geomagnetic
data i'll probably adjust your noise and you don't
care too much so i thought i'd do a quick overview
of kind of what space weather is and why it kind
of matters to me and then i'll talk a little
bit about the research that i've been doing
uh into power grids and pipelines
and then talk a little bit about
some projects that we're involved
in and for operational services
so space weather it's essentially just a term
um to describe the variability of conditions
in near earth space environment and specifically
here we're using it to refer to conditions that
have an impact on technology infrastructure and
people either in space or on or near the ground
um so this is the kind of classic image from issa
that i'm sure you've all come across before which
is showing all the different impacts of space
whether on different kind of types of technology
so the things that are obvious like satellites
and astronauts because they're up in space
that are affected by space weather um either
directly by radiation or degradation sometimes
with things like single event upsets which can
kind of affect what a satellite is doing and
maybe confuse the operators down on the ground
because they maybe lose the satellite for a
little bit um as we move further down into
the ionosphere there's then space where they
can cause lots of enhanced currents and
other disturbances within the ionosphere
that then make it very difficult for satellite
signals to pass through so that can lead to um
you know errors in satellite communications it
can lead to a reduction of accuracy of things like
gps which isn't going to affect you and your car
with your satellite navigation system because it's
not that accurate anyway but there are lots of
systems around the world that rely on very precise
gps so if your gps signal is getting delayed in
the ionosphere that's going to have a an impact
and reduce your accuracy which which can be
really important and if we move a bit further down
again down to the to the ground that's the
bit where i'm going to talk about today so
space where they can cause these kind of
induced geoelectric fields which then can
lead to geomagnetically induced currents
in things like power lines and of course it
can reduce accuracy of directional drilling
so if you're not aware of a lot of drilling
activities because they're underground gps doesn't
really work and having to use um other precision
ways of navigating your well path on the
ground are quite expensive so they actually
use the magnetic field obviously if there's a big
geomagnetic storm going on that's going to affect
their measurements and therefore where they think
their drill puff is going so it's important that
they understand um whether there's a storm going
to happen or not so in terms of ground effects
there's kind of two main causes of space weather
impacts of the earth so the first is coronal holes
um and these are regions on the sun's surface
that appeared darker under lots of different
filters um because they're a little bit colder
and have a slightly lower density plasma than
the average in the corona and they're linked
to open magnetic field lines so basically that
just means it's easier for things to escape into
the solar wind so in the solar wind you get from
these corona holes you get these fast patches and
because everything's rotating these fast patches
hit the slower patches from before and you can
get compression regions so when that sweep past
the earth you get a kind of a shock um but you
can get a shock depending on how fast they are
and you can get lots of disturbances in the
magnetic field now crown holes don't tend to cause
massive gemetic storms but they can be significant
the other main one is coronal mass ejections so
coronal mass ejections are usually associated
with solar flares or occasionally filament
eruptions although both of these can be happen
independently of coronal mass ejections as well
um so solar flares are just these really bright
um releases of energy which they're classified
in terms of the x-ray flux that they release at
the time and then filaments so the filament here
is just this dark string above the surface of the
sun and if i just play this video you can see it
erupting quite spectacularly so they can lead to
what we call a coronal mass ejection so what is
a coronal mass ejection well um here's
one going off here which i think you can
i just pause it you can see so there's a
nice um big bubble of stuff basically leaving
the solar surface so the sun is
approximately where the white circle is
and the satellite has a what's called an
occulting disk so effectively we're looking
at an eclipse from space but it's a man-made
eclipse because we've just blocked out the sun
so this is the sun's corona and you can see
there's a big bubble this is the coronal
mass ejection heading off the side of the sun in
this case um and that's full of lots of charged
particles and lots of solar magnetic field that's
all jumbled up in this case if it was heading off
towards the side it's not such a problem but
here's one that was heading towards the earth
which went so fast you can barely see it
so i'll just slow that down so you can see
this is what we'd call a full halo coronal mass
ejection it's called a full halo just because it
goes all the way around the sun and this one was
definitely heading towards us because you could
see all this insulation on the camera so this
is one of those kind of space weather effects
of all those charged particles hitting the camera
afterwards and you can see that over time that's
gonna that's gonna do some damage but as i said
a bit i'm interested in is the actual coronal
mass ejection so that can take anywhere between
around kind of 14 hours to five days to get to us
depending on the speed of that that corona mass
ejection and when they get to the earth they cause
geomagnetic storms so again as i'm sure you're
all very aware this is a kind of nice quiet day
um curve from uh from one of our
geomagnetic observatories this is esthermia
and here's the same observatory but on a
stormy day and these you know the storm itself
the variations are much larger than they were on
a quiet day i mean they're still small compared to
the background field but it's this the rapid
variations that are really really the issue
and that's because it causes electric fields to be
reduced in the ground which then causes currents
to flow in ground-based infrastructure
so power networks pipelines railways etc
so in 2012 this was recognized by the uk
government as being a genuine risk to the uk
and so space weather is circled here as number 19
on the risk register in the latest edition saying
that there is a relatively high likelihood
of a space weather a big space weather event
affecting the uk with what they
call level c level impact so a
kind of relatively high level of impact
so just for reference 25 here is at the
impact of a global pandemic um so space weather
is kind of considered a similar likelihood to
that but hopefully not quite as impactful
certainly not for as long we would hope um so
in terms of mitigating space well then the
first thing we can do is to forecast it
so there's lots and lots of different um ways
of looking at the sun now so there's quite a
few satellites or continuously monitoring
the sun either looking directly kind of at
the sun itself through different filters
to so we can see when there's sunspots
or you know these images from soho that i just
showed you looking for coronal mass ejections
and disturbances in the corona and there's
also the new discover satellite which is an
operational satellite measuring the solar wind
at the l1 point at all times and then there are
other things like the ghost satellites which
measure the x-ray flux so they give you that
size of flares that we've seen now there has been
an increasing amount of solar monitoring happening
over the last few years which is fantastic but for
the most part they're all based either at the l1
point so between the sun and the earth or actually
orbiting the earth so we kind of have quite a
one-dimensional view of the sun so this this plot
here is just kind of imagine we're looking down
on the solar system effectively so pretty much our
only viewpoint is from just in front of the earth
or at the earth now there is the stereo satellites
which so marked here as a and b so they have over
time gradually drifted round earth orbit so a head
started ahead of the earth that's why it's that's
what the a stands for and it's gone all the way
around now past the back of the sun and it's now
behind the earth effectively and the behind one
started the other way and it went all the way
around unfortunately we've lost contact with
stereo behind uh since it went behind the
sun so we're no longer getting data from it but
right now stereo a is giving us a brilliant view
of the sun because by looking at this kind of
different angle you can get much better estimate
of the speed of say cmes when they're coming
towards the earth and it also measures the solar
wind um before it gets to the air so because the
sun is obviously rotating if something on the sun
here is rotating around it's going to sweep past
the head before it gets to earth so that's great
but that's a science mission and as i say the
whole point of that science mission was that it's
continuously moving around earth orbit so it's
not always in that position there are plans to
launch a new satellite so esa has plans to
launch a satellite to the l5 point which is
near where stereo head is at the moment um
so that will be brilliant when it goes up
but in terms of kind of actual data
we're maybe a little bit lacking in
in what we need for really really good forecasts
of space weather and just incidentally that visa
mission um is currently looking for a name
so if anybody has any ideas of good names
for easy missions you can go on and submit
it on the esa website at the moment i think
as well as uh satellite data there's also a
growing suite of other data and models and
forecasts um which again is brilliant that we're
we're getting so much better and they're all
improving but we're still a long way from really
being able to forecast base where they're in a
kind of prompt and meaningful way so for example
this model here is called the enlil model
and that's great you can see so these blobs
here are two different cmes that launched and
it gives you an estimate of arrival time and
the velocity of the solar wind when it gets
to earth and all that kind of stuff but the
problem with models like this at the moment
is firstly they need the data to go
in so you need to have got the date
enough data back from say the satellites to
be able to analyze your coronal mass ejection
which takes time and then once you've analyzed
it you need somebody to have put it into the
model and set the model running and then the
model itself takes around six hours to run
so that takes you know that's quite a big chunk of
time you know by the time you're gonna get results
it's probably gonna be around 10 hours or so since
the launch of the cme and the fastest known cme to
ever reach us was around 14 hours so that's not
going to give you a huge amount of warning time
if we need to do something drastic in terms of
a huge cme coming our way um but it's improving
all the time and i see the models themselves
are improving all time and there's lots of
very clever people working on trying to forecast
flares and cmes before they even happen which is
kind of the ultimate really in terms of being
able to to respond to one of these threats
and this this on the right hand side this is
the european space agency's new space weather
service portal which anyone can register
to to look at it has lots and lots of new
uh products um including things like forecasts of
dbdt but they're um yeah they're still very much
a kind of work in progress and they're
quite large broad scale so at bgs we
do do a three day ahead forecast every day um
and that goes to our stakeholders so people like
national grid who run the power network and people
who do directional drilling for the oil industry
but it also goes up on our website so you can
you know access it publicly at this this link
and we tweet it as well and then if
there is if we do expect a big storm to
come we also have an alert service so you
should can subscribe to that our website
or we have a separate um twitter account
as well because not everybody wants to
hear the uh everyone wants to see the space
weather forecast every day when it mostly just
says quiet although some people apparently find
that very soothing um but we have the aurora alert
separately for people who just want to know
when there's something interesting going on
and then other things we do we run a kind
of operational um now caste system for
geomagnetically induced currents in the grid
for national grid um and we also give them
other information like what's happening in the
magnetic field and the solar wind at any time
and then we also run other pages like this so
this is for the met office so the met office has
the most up-to-date information because they fit
um in terms of the government they own the space
where the risk for the uk so they need to be well
informed about what's happening both on the ground
and up in space and then this is our contribution
to the the esa portal so there's lots and lots of
kind of forecasting operational work going on
and they're improving all the time and there's
new models and new forecasts being added all
the time okay so in terms of our research on um
gics um again for anyone who who doesn't know
what happens during geomagnetic storm you get
this electrical current in the ionosphere
which then induces a varying magnetic field
perpendicular which then induces an electric
field in the ground and electric fields like to
find nice easy routes to flow so they find power
grids which are by design um as low resistance as
possible for electricity to flow along because
that's that's their purpose and so gses tend
to find these points and they flow into the
earthing points of transformers and then through
the grid and for the most part they they act like
quasi dc currents but the power grid is set up to
cope with ac currents so what can happen is that
can lead to things like voltage instabilities
which can cause problems within the grid itself
and the main thing that can do is actually to
trip protective relays because generally in you
know every other day a voltage instability would
suggest that there's some other problem so it
will shut down or might switch off something or to
shut down a transformer the problem with space
weather is if you have glc's in the network
they're kind of through the whole network and
if you start unplugging bits of that network
you then concentrate the gics into specific
bits of the network which can then really cause
problems um in the absolute worst case
scenario gics push transformers out
of their normal operating capacity and that
means they heat up and in the very worst case
that causes some quite significant damage so this
is a transformer coil which should be all you
know nice and smooth and metallic and you can see
here it's it's basically got so hot that it's um
sparked and burnt parts of the transform so
this transformer had to be completely replaced
due to space other event and transformers are
not easy things to replace they are very large
very expensive and there aren't that many of
them surplus at any one time so again another
issue of space weather is that it it has quite
global impacts so in a really big event there
is a a slight worry that if enough power grids
lost transformers it would take a very long time
to replace them because they just they don't
sit around on shelves waiting to be to be used
although the awareness around it has
improved a lot so i think some people
there are there's more resilience being built
into systems so there's more transformers at each
substation if they're a key very important
substation anyway so how do we actually
model it well it takes there's kind of
three stages so we start with some inputs
then we create some models and then we create
some some proper outputs the actual gic
so we start with data from
observatory so here's a whole
range of observatories that are kind of vaguely in
the region of the uk so some of these are marked
on this map as the white triangle some of them
are slightly out of shot here and what we do
is we take off a quiet time mean because
we're not too worried about the main field
um what we want to capture is these these rapid
variations and then we can take all of this data
and then we use what's called the spherical
elementary current systems to interpolate
the magnetic field across the uk so we can get
a picture of what the magnetic field is doing
right across the uk in both in the
horizontal components so x and x and y
we then also need a conductivity model so at the
moment we use um a model based on the geological
map of the uk so what we've effectively said is
we expect each rock unit to have approximately
a certain conductivity and that is built into a
model um which is meant to represent approximately
the top three kilometers of the surface and then
underneath that we have a series of 1d models um
so they only vary with depth based again very
loosely on kind of bedrock geology of the uk
um and we call that our kind of thin sheet model
so we can use our thin sheet model where you
so you effectively use the 1d models to get the
electric field due to the magnetic changes and
then the thin sheet on top redistributes that
current uh to give you where the the highest
electric fields on the surface would be which
means we can include kind of coastal effects so
you can see that sometimes the electric field
kind of builds up a little bit along the coast
as you might expect so as a slight aside from
that one thing we are doing at the moment is
to try and improve our electric field
model so the thin sheet model is great
in terms of its it gives you some of the detail
um whilst still being relatively computationally
efficient so a 3d model would be great but they're
very computationally expensive to run and at
the moment we just don't have that level of data
for the uk um so there's three main ways to derive
ground electric field so first is measurement so
we do now have long term measurements of the
electric field at our three uk observatories
and that's great to have because it gives us
something we can validate our models with and
to do that we just take some num non-polarizing uh
electrodes and we put them in a kind of solution
to again help reduce polarization even more
and you put them up you know put two nodes
um apart in the east-west direction and two in
the north south directions this is the setup at
heartland and you can measure the electric
fields and that's um been really good but
there are some problems so the data quality isn't
always brilliant because we're definitely learning
as we go and it's been improving as we go but
there are gaps and problems that we know we need
to address and the other thing is of course you're
not necessarily just measuring the space weather
so here's a plot from heartland on the right so
this is a stack plot for june 2013 so each line is
a different day just plotted against time and you
can really clearly see the tidal effect in there
because there's a huge tidal range very close to
the observatory so that's again just something
a little complication that we need to think about
when we're comparing our model to our measurements
uh the other way as we've already slightly
discussed is that you can derive ground electric
field through modelling so as at the moment we
use the thin sheet model um and we are trying to
work on improving that and then the last one is
these empty impedance transfer functions um in
combination with magnetic field observations
and we're starting to do a little bit more
of that so here's an example from um
whitehaven in scotland where we've
now got some good mt measurements but one of
the issues we've had for the uk is there's a
the measurements we have are relatively
sparse but there's a few programs from a
couple of different products um over the last
few years and going into the future where
we've been trying to firstly find legacy data
but also take new measurements so we can really
improve that and that's i think probably
the way we're headed is to try and
really use mt impedance transfer functions
a lot more than we do and just as a little
example here's an example from a paper we've
just released showing some comparisons between
the measurements so the blue lines here for
lerwick estamia and then heartland at the bottom
our measurements of electric field the green is
the empty impedance and the red is the thin sheet
and you can see in most cases we're kind
of we're capturing the essence of the storm
but we're maybe slightly underestimating the
peaks and missing a little bit of the detail
at times the mt from the empty impedances
do a lot better uh than the thin sheet we're
definitely underestimating with the thin sheet so
it's an active area where we're trying to improve
okay so the next thing we need once we've got
our electric field is our power network model so
we construct a power network model using the
10-year statement that's published
every year by national grid
and that has information about the resistance of
the lines and the resistance of the transformers
we still have to make assumptions about the
earthing resistance but it does give us a huge
amount of information we're now able to model that
to a much better level than we have in the past
and at the moment power lines are then
just approximated by straight lines
between the grids because that's the
information in that statement however
i am just now working on actually being able to
include the full path um between each substation
which will make the slight at least a slight
difference to our results because it changes
the length of the line to start off with and it
also changes which bits of the electric field
are kind of inducing currents in that particular
line and then once we've got all of that we can
plug it into our git model and get gic out
at the end so here's an example for the march
1989 storm you can see some fairly significant
gic at certain substations around the uk
and you notice this you know mostly red
on one side are mostly blue on the other
side and that's just because the kind of
inducing electric field is mostly east west
in this case so the currents flow into the grid
on one side and out of the grid on the other side
um okay the other thing we've been working on
much more recently is um the effect that that
has on pipelines so unlike power grids which as i
say can kind of catastrophically fail during the
storm very quickly the effect on pipelines
is a bit more gradual it's more about the
corrosion rate so by pipelines are protected steel
pipelines particularly protected from corrosion
using what's called galvanic protection and it's
just about maintaining the potential of the pipe
um at a level approximately one volt below that
of the ground and so that you protect the pipe
from the corrosion and it stops there and it stops
you getting currents flowing from one to the other
um but during a space weather event or even
it doesn't even have to be that big a storm
you can quite quickly override that protection so
potentially you're then increasing the corrosion
rate compared to what you know the pipeline is
planned to deal with so that can shorten the life
of pipes and in some cases particularly if there's
already been a little bit of damage it could then
um really exacerbate the situation and make
your pipeline fail much more quickly than you
expect it to and there is there is a case in new
zealand which you may remember was in the news
a few years ago that the main fuel pipeline to
auckland airport suddenly failed one day and it
caused a huge headache for the airport for quite
some time um and there is a suggestion that um
although the pipeline had already been damaged
there was a scratch across it from previous
uh construction work i think a digger had
at some point managed to scratch the pipe
but the failure only happened a few days after a
really big storm um geomagnetic storm so there is
there has been some suggestion that perhaps
the the storm contributed to increasing the
corrosion and was kind of the final final
straw so here's our new model for the uk so
on the left here is just model i've taken
again from open source data on national grid
gases website uh giving a full pipeline network
for the high pressure gas transmission system
uh with kind of where we think the different
lines end and where they connect to other nodes
um and then here on the right is the
practical potentials that we've modeled
for the grid four fitness was during a
storm again and you can see we get some
really quite significant you know well well
over 40 volt pipe sole potentials in certain
places which is much much larger than the the
one volt range that the galvanic protection
is trying to keep the pipeline at so it's
definitely something that we need to do more
work on and to understand better as there's lots
and lots of assumptions in this pipe but it's
it's definitely worth doing and
understanding especially as the
um gas pipelines in the uk start to get
that bit older we need to know that they're
not going to suddenly fail um okay so
moving on to another little product so
we've recently been involved in the swigs project
which is a a big um four-year project called um
space where the impact on ground-based systems
the big nerc funded project um and as part of that
we've started making our own gic measurements
because we do have some gse measurements from
the from scottish power but they're at these
only at these four sites in the grid so it's not
overly representative of the grid and we
do have to remember to ask for the data
otherwise it gets deleted after a couple of
weeks it's you know far from a continuous
set of data that we can just pull into
and we don't necessarily fully understand
what that data is whether it's for a
single transformer or whether it's the
the jrc at through the the earthing point or well
what so what we've started doing now is making our
own measurements that we control and we understand
and we do this with the differential magnetometer
method um where you basically put one magnetometer
under the power line one at a distance away
and you align them so you know
they're both aligned the same way
and you assume that any difference
between the two is due to the gic
in the line because they should be close
enough that they're experiencing the same um
external magnetic field but far enough apart that
only one of them is being affected by the line
um and you can read about that in the
paper that um julena recently had published
and that has been really useful we started
to look at um that compared to our model
so whitehaven here is this this cross here
and these are the the lines you see for that
um under that line so we can do the
the measured data using that that dmm
system compared to the model and it shows
that actually we're not we're not too far
off there's still definitely work to do on our
model and particularly the input electric field
but actually it's a surprisingly good good result
really and then we can also compare that um with
data at the at the gic site as well so totalness
is one of the sites that we've got gic for
um okay so just as a kind of final point the um
we're also involved in a couple of big
projects where we're bringing together
all that research and our own expertise
of doing operational space weather
into a much more kind of large-scale organized
system so this swimmer set of activities is set up
it's a joint initiative by nerc and stfc but it's
also supported by a few government bodies and the
met office where the aim is to basically improve
the uk's capability at forecasting and now casting
space weather um so for the first time we're going
to be using so models like uh gorgon which can
um is a big complicated mr mhr model to give solar
winds uh sorry to give my metospheric uh impacts
to then give us the ground magnetic field
which then we can uh forecast gics and we've
not been able to forecast glc's like that
in the in the uk and that's um something
that we're working hard on now and hopefully once
we can link that all up that will be a really
um really fantastically useful system for the uk
and the other project is called euphoria so again
it's a very kind of similar idea where you've got
this kind of sun to earth chain of space weather
and this is a big european model so you
have these mhd models of the corona and
then the solar wind and the magnetosphere
which then leads us to gic prediction
um so you know here's our kind of first work
on that where we've got a conductivity model
for europe admittedly much less sophisticated
than what i was just talking about for the uk
but that can then give us electric field house of
maps and then i've also constructed a gic map uh
uh jesse power grid model for the whole of
europe so we can then get grc out at the end
of this project hopefully um and yeah that's a
summary and i realized i've talked for slightly
longer than i meant to so i'll just leave that
there and see if anybody has any questions
excellent thank you very much gemma we can
all um give jim a virtual round of applause
uh through them for actually
really really interesting talk
um so i'll open uh the floor to questions
um so you can raise your hand um
via the zoom uh functions there for questions
for gemma but we'll kick off with one um
in the chat from from gunther um who's asking
um are there or alyssa gunther do you want to
read out your your question yes first thank you
very much for interesting talk i am glad that
finally there is also talk from the space physics
because it's kind of what's missing in here in
this community and my question is more like a
little basic one i'm sure it's probably but yeah
since you didn't talk too much about it uh i hang
on it's uh it's about uh you know the there is a
soil cycle and usually every 11 years there's
a change of the polarity and i i wonder you
know what would be the next topology for the
cycle 25 is there any um attempts to predict
the you know how the cycle will be intense and
i think at least for mars it's very different
if the if the if there is like a north the south
topology for the events that are happening on the
ground of mars and i think it's probably the same
case also for the earth that it has to do with the
way how the how the magnetic fields reconnect
but if you could clarify that please um yeah
so in terms of the solar cycle we've we've just
entered the latest solar cycle so it's 25. um
the consensus opinion so there's a group that
all get together each solar cycle to predict
the next solar cycle so their their consensus is
that we will see a solar cycle that is similar
to cycle 24 so the one that's just happened
there is one new paper and the name of the
the name of which completely escapes me
but i'm sure i can find it who have used
a new method of forecasting and they're actually
predicting a much larger more active cycle um but
that's a brand new technique and they're not
um i guess we'll have to wait and see whether
they're right or not but the kind of consensus
opinion is it'll be similar to the previous one
uh in terms of the the polarity of the
so which part of the cycle we're in
that doesn't matter too much so the the polarity
of the sun spots on the sun i don't think it has
a huge impact on um how effective space weather
is what does matter is the angle of the um solar
magnetic field at the point that it reaches the
earth so any coronal mass ejection can contain
that kind of interplanetary magnetic field but
if it's strongly southwards then that connects
very well to the earth's magnetic field
and you get a much bigger storm as a result
but it's not necessarily dependent on
the solar cycle which whether we're in a
solar cycle where it's predominantly norfolk's
opportunities hopefully that answers what you
thank you i appreciate it i have more questions
but i'll wait until someone else asked some
questions yes so i assuming richard holm will
have a question since he's unmuted and the video
is on and you go richard hey gemma um i was really
impressed by your modelling of the events and you
had your thin sheet and your mt um uh models
could you possibly zip back to that briefly
there is wasn't he was that him
so back so forward one again so see the data
oh okay yeah so so looking at those yeah as
you're quite right the thin sheet is smaller
magnitude but it is you know it's pretty good
um so could you try just kind of um data modelling
fit where you just scaled and maybe had a
scaling as a function of um intensity or scaling
as a function of period of the variations
and therefore avoid having to be too clever
because my brain isn't good enough for mt um as
the mt people who talk to me will know um and just
just just do a heuristic fit yeah it's definitely
definitely an option um we've kind of only just
really started to get properly with the data that
we've measured and unfortunately as i say that
the data are a little bit um gappy and of poor
quality at times this is one of the good examples
but yeah we could definitely go through and find
you know patches that are good and see if we can
come up with some kind of scaling yeah that's
that's yeah i see student project you may
remember being forced to do student projects
thank you jim thank you thanks richard um well
i'm going to quickly squeeze in with a question
of my own before we jump over to anybody else
but you know when you're doing your the maps of
the the power grid um you know you're doing it
in a very good fashion but then you're saying
you're you're going down to the detail and
mapping out the details of the network i mean
how are you actually doing that are there the
detailed records available that you can use um
yes so on again open source from national grid's
website we can get shape files for england and
wales which actually do detail the path of
the lines um and i have almost managed to get
those into our network and there's also other
sources so for scotland we can get so open
street map there's lots of very dedicated
people have mapped the paths of power lines
near them um so we're looking
at whether we can include those
but the first a little bit of crowdsourced data
then going into it yeah it's pretty cool yes great
uh so so gunther did you have
another question you said
yes i have a quick question i know that
a lot of this space whether events are
connected with the process which is not very
well known for this fellow magnetic community
it's called the reconnection and i know that
you know a lot of you know there is some kind
almost looks like there's some kind of a magic
around it how it's actually happening because
suddenly you have a stationary ions near the
sun and suddenly there is an acceleration of
that ion to the alpha and speed which is i mean
probably tens of kilometers per second and if
you could clarify it or not to tell how this
process is important for this space weather
um yeah simplify so yeah
i have to admit i'm not as
good on reconnection as i'd like to be because as
you say it does tend to get presented as as magic
a little bit and i'm happy to go with that but um
i think a lot of it's around um kind of magnetic
tension effectively so the when the solar wind
if it's pointing southwards it connects really
well to the basically the front of the magnetic
field and it essentially kind of opens it up
um pulls it to the back and then at some point
you know there's a huge amount of energy and that
field line wants to reconnect and that's where
you throw huge amounts of energy into the system
um beyond that i'm not sure i can really give you
a much better description it's okay let me give
you another question which is a little bit related
but not exactly it there's a moon that kind of
goes around and i always wonder if for example
if the moon is between the earth and the sun
i'm sure there must be a plasma sphere
because of the moon is like an obstacle to the
solar wind and does that plasma sphere
affects in any way the space weather
that is a good question not that i'm aware of but
yeah i guess it might do um
to some extent but yeah it's not
something i've ever really seen
any research on so i can't
give you a clear answer on that
and then my next question thank you is uh the
ulf uh the ultra low frequency waves that are
generated in uh uh i always was kind of
like wondering what's the power spectrum
uh what's where are the frequencies that are you
know i i know that there is a the lower longer the
frequency of electromagnetic waves
the more penetration to the ground
uh but if there is any way that you could
uh say something about the spectrum how
the spectrum look like of these waves
that are coming in because of the solar
the space weather um so i'm trying to think now
definitely got more brain on um yeah the so the
kind of space for the effects that we tend
to worry about are kind of somewhere between
uh
a few seconds up to a few hours
generally um the stuff that in terms
of affecting the gic we're only really
interested in the kind of that kind of around
one hertz kind of plus or minus a little bit um
but yeah again i'm not sure i can give you a much
better answer than that right now well uh let me
thank you very much we've got we've got time for
one last quick question from from uh got here and
then i'm conscious of time we'll need to sort
of wrap it up so uh gautier would you like to
to answer ask your question yeah i'll ask it
not answer it yeah thanks a lot thanks a lot
for the presentation sorry i was a bit late
so maybe some of the information i missed um
i i had actually two two quick questions one
related to the previous one and and i was
just wondering which is the frequency which
is most efficient in terms of producing uh
problems in other words when you have a geometric
event i mean it's it's it has a wide spectrum
which other frequency we need to worry most about
and perhaps the answer is different for electric
grids and pipelines i don't know and the second
one was uh one of your slides where you're showing
the results of the electric field produced
on the pipelines the structure was most uh
much less intuitive to me than the one you showed
for the electric grids so we have these red dots
that come around and i just wanted to ask you what
was the reason for this is this because of changes
in the resistivity of the pipeline structure or
is this related to the geometric field itself
uh a little bit of both so it's partly
the resistivity of the pipeline itself
it's partly the length of a pipeline that are
fully connected so the longer the pipeline that is
connected then the the larger the currents um that
you get and therefore the larger the potentials
that you can also get and yeah i think in this
case it was also partly related to the electric
field in the background as well so i think i think
this was from a storm where there was a strong
electric field or the strongest electric field is
kind of across here in the uk um and the longest
pipeline in the network kind of comes right
down here so we tend to find the largest psps
around that basically in terms of the the kind
of periods that matter the jury's still out a
little bit and certainly for pipelines it's
something that i want to look at is whether
some of the kind of i just i suspect the really
high frequency things don't really matter to
the pipelines because they're kind of on and
off so quickly that it's not going to affect
um corrosion in terms of gic again we tend to
talk about kind of tens of seconds up to a few
minutes maybe up to 10 minutes that kind of range
being the important range but again there's still
a little bit of debate around whether you know
you can the really high frequency stuff is just
so quick that actually it doesn't have
time to produce a response in the system
and actually whether it's some of the slightly
longer periods fluctuations that that matter
but yeah kind of around that kind of as i say
10 seconds to a few minutes kind of the bit we
tend to be more concerned about and for for power
grids excellent thank you very much um so in an
interesting time i think we can uh wrap up our uh
question in discussion session so thank you very
much gemma we can all give her another a virtual
round of applause for a really interesting uh a
really interesting talk um so just before
um we completely uh come to a close today
um just a a reminder um that um our next two
seminars will be in two weeks and then in another
two weeks and our speakers are still too uh still
to be confirmed um but we're always looking for
uh more speakers um covering all topics uh
across uh earth science magnetisms uh and
and in particular we encourage uh early career
uh scientists so if you're interested in giving
a presentation or you know somebody who might
be able to give a really good presentation
please get in touch with us uh and also just
a final reminder that um all of the seminars
are recorded and they're available on our youtube
channel so if you miss out on any of the seminars
in the past you can catch up with them all
on youtube and thank you all very much again
for for joining this week's magnets and
we'll see you see you next time cheers